Amir Ali Jiwani

Software Craftsman



¶ 17 Ashbourne Boulevard, Donnybrook, 3064, Melbourne (AU), Victoria

https://www.linkedin.com/in/amiralijiwani/

amirali.jiwani89@gmail.com

Q (0061) 497484475

in amiralijiwani 🖸 aajiwani

About

A software enthusiast -- Developing software for human beings as a human for over a decade. I have got a chance to visit various domains and technologies during this time; The experience has shaped the way I think and work now. I like to create software and help other developers like me around. I have recently been interested in connecting the dots, making concepts available in layman's terms and helping bridge the gap between specialists (usually developers) and other stakeholders. I believe everyone attached to a concept should have a right to completely and concisely understand it, enabling them to contribute to the purpose. I have been working on recent technologies like NodeJS, React, Docker, Kubernetes, Electron, and others. My main focus is on problem-solving, irrespective of the platform usually. However, knowing platforms give me an edge over someone that might not.

Experience

SEEK

February 2023 - Present

Lead Engineer

Working with other platform teams and residing under the online identity space, leading a team of engineers to build the right tools engineered in a reasonable fashion

Examplify being a senior team member; Available, willing to help and leading by example Helping the journey of organization to fulfil the goal of unifying systems to the selected one

Architect various big and small pieces of the system wherever necessary. It involves rewriting several heavy-weight components to fit the need; sometimes, it may require a clean slate implementation of the parts of the system

Voice out an opinion that helps the team to think in the right direction

Partner with Staff engineer and Engineering manager to help steer team in the right focus area

Nourishing junior members with SEEK values and behaviors

Participate in conversations with various system stakeholders to achieve the best outcome possible

Articulate problems that are understandable and approachable by teams and stakeholders

Help multiple actors in the team to understand and get around the problem in layman terms

Propose architecture for various system needs, implement them, and vocalize them within multiple teams

PicklesAuctions

July 2022 - February 2023

Senior Principal Engineer

Leading several teams, working on solutions based upon distributed computing to make the e-commerce scene under the global travel space alive

Examplify being a senior team member, not limited to the delivery but as someone colleagues can look up to for holding values

Be a catalyst to execute and deliver the system from the current state to the imagined one Architect various big and small pieces of the system wherever necessary. It involves rewriting several heavy-weight components to fit the need; sometimes, it may require a clean slate implementation of the parts of the system

Infuse and practice a culture of learning while performing the duties

Participate in conversations with various system stakeholders to achieve the best outcome possible

Articulate problems that are understandable and approachable by teams and stakeholders

Take on the ownership of various projects within the ecosystem to deliver and maintain them

Help relatively junior team members have the spark to shine and help them shine Propose architecture for various system needs, implement them, and vocalize them within multiple teams

Agoda March 2022 - July 2022

Software Engineering Manager

Leading several teams, working on solutions based upon distributed computing to make the e-commerce scene under the global travel space alive

Working with teams to migrate long-running legacy systems to a newer and a better stack Keeping track of the learning abilities of my team so that they can progress in their respective careers and interests

Having 1:1s to shape up the team culture and align them with essential matters at the organization

Build a mindset and culture of quality first; Owning our stuff and converting them to quality artefacts and systems

Help the organization envision what moving away from legacy could mean and preach the benefits within the team(s)

Help the team understand Agility at work and take them through ceremonies; This helps the team give their best following sprints

Making an effort around organizational values, so it lives within the team and work we do.

Gaditek March 2021 - March 2022

Software Engineering Manager

Provided leadership across the engineering organization for the aspects of hiring, processes, architecture, grooming individuals and solving complex problems

Introduced a hiring process and its custodianship (aka The Hiring Squad!)
Enabled the eco-system of documentation keeping and taking tools along with helping the team to use them day-in-day-out

Conducted 1:1s with team members to keep their inspirations and motivations up Helped to bootstrap various products for a quick test with the upcoming consumer markets for the organization

Been a part of the team and the solution for complex problems like NotificationCenter, Auth provider selection and payment gateway solution

Created and vocalized a process of hiring interns and turning them into fellow beings Led and represented the engineering department of the organization

Proactively participated in converting an old-school organization to an organization with agility

Helped and created career progression for various individuals in the organization Proactively involved me with HR to discuss and demystify challenging problems Introduced and have been the most potent catalyst in changing our product platform to be the cross-platform product

Enabled ways to bring in new dimensions to the product evolution, which were held back because of the absence of engineering leadership

Focus on quality deliverables -- Provided guidance to bring in an appropriate SDLC I got involved and got my hands dirty with architecture decisions at various organizational levels

SEEK

February 2020 - March 2021

Software Engineering Manager

SEEK is a diverse group of companies that have a unified purpose to help people live more fulfilling and productive working lives and help organisations succeed.

Contributed to SEEKs overall product & technology strategy and aligned systems with that strategy

Ensured that systems were fit for purpose, well-architected and followed current SEEK development practices

Maintained platform health by ensuring that our systems are secure, reliable, resilient and cost-effective

Drove customer focus to ensure that we deliver excellent outcomes for our customers Commenced and maintained a high performing team culture that values collaboration, learning and continual improvement

Acted as an enabler; Grew my team's technical skills and leadership capabilities through coaching and mentoring. This involves having 1:1s with my teammates

Lead by example, Which required me to get my hands dirty when needed

Unblocked the team with whatever it took, having complete ownership of maintaining healthy teams

Celebrated successes and learnt from the failures; propagated the culture through the teams and exemplified it for the rest of the organization

Paired with the Principal Engineer of the team to understand the climate and the team's problems

Participated in and retro-ed the core hiring process through a centralized hiring squad Helped the org to move fast to the ecosystem of global products; Away from the local products which we have been dealing with for the past 25+ years

SEEK

July 2018 - January 2020

Lead Software Architect

SEEK is a diverse group of companies that have a unified purpose to help people live more fulfilling and productive working lives and help organisations succeed.

Been the catalyst for transforming the organization

Performed the duties as the JavaScript coach for the organization

Advocated for and implemented software best practices

Have been the communicator for various teams to maintain their health; sometimes preached the organization's values

Participated as a core in hiring new and experienced talents

Propagated automation as a culture rather than an option

Moved legacy code and data to cloud via lift & shift, greenfield and brownfield methodologies

Performed the duties of deciding and validating sensible defaults for the organization Pushed cloud-first approach in the org, living in an environment of Infra ops With the help of fellow architects, I invested time in a flourishing framework of single identity throughout SEEK systems; We did this through educating, enabling, and supporting the needful tools for the teams

Created several SDKs for a single identity solution within Seek with complete automation and tests. Later helped teams adopt them into various systems

Exact

September 2016 - January 2018

Senior Software Engineer (Full-Stack)

We are Exact. We make smart business software. We are entrepreneurial and dream big, just like you. We help and encourage anyone we work with to always be the best version of themselves.

Helped to come up with an end-to-end pipeline to build and release the product Performed various tasks, including coding, building, testing, releasing and debugging the product

Made massive use of automation, including development and release cycles Helped to produce tools that are helpful during the lifecycle of the product. Usually as a need to support the development

Helped POC the product initially with our customers to set up our product owner for the product's success

Created a framework single-handedly to help my fellow teammates with the needs of React Navigation and enable them to flourish their work distributedly and without flaws Created and open-sourced a library that behaves as a HOC for navigation matters around React space

Created an in-house tool (based on ElectronJS) for various development teams that helps with the consumption of APIs without open API specs (legacy systems)

Hexosys

January 2016 - September 2016

Senior Software Engineer

Accomplishing more than 150 main products as cutting-edge technology protocol/bus analyzers, reveals great ability of HexoSys to delivering new projects within the field of expertise with complete maturity and high competitive to the global high-tech market.

Helped in a complete overhaul and rewriting of parts of the Albaloo product Added the ability to target users through multi communication channels (SMS, emails, mobile notifications etc.)

Helped product with identifying with and implementing the ability of geo fencing the ads in the current platform

Introduced a custom framework on top of Laravel's current implementation to support custom JavaScript loading in the layout

Initialized and laid the basis for automation in the project, simplifying and making some tedious tasks process-oriented

Helped teams with mocks to let them produce their artefacts accordingly. Later replaced with the accurate data bounded by the contracts

Helped in versioning the APIs so that various teams in the organization consume their needed bits and are working harmoniously

Experian

July 2014 - November 2015

Senior Software Developer

Accomplishing more than 150 main products as cutting-edge technology protocol/bus analyzers, reveals great ability of HexoSys to delivering new projects within the field of expertise with complete maturity and high competitive to the global high-tech market.

Assisted developers with a better approach to the problem at hand. I have to talk with my Team lead and the Architect to finalise a software architecture decision

Primarily worked on the architectural aspects of the code, but I sometimes had the requirement to fix bugs and further minor changes

Got myself certified with CITA-F to get relevant in the architecture escape and software practices

Helped with adopting EHAB in various parts of our legacy application

Debugged and fixed various system parts containing loads of stored procedures and complex SQL queries

Pi-Labs
Chief Technology Officer

Our passion for mobile software and our ability to deliver engaging solutions has given us much acclaim. Early adoption of Windows Phone 7 meant we were one of the first companies globally to have produced an app for the Microsoft Marketplace. Yet, our expertise encompasses the breadth of the smartphone ecosystems, including iOS, Android and Palm's WebOS.

This was my earliest position as a technical leader, and I was going through significant learning

Helped organization with various services-based projects; Dealt with multiple platforms and technologies

Created, architected and maintained a homegrown idea that later shifted to become Garfield's official game, Feed Garfield. The internal project name was Candy Pot. It was a team effort

Created, architected and maintained an idea in collaboration with our partner. It was a video and audio processing app; These were early days when Snapchat didn't exist; The project was named Gulf Talk

Worked on an aggregator banking solution known as Mobank for UK based banks. Clients were able to control their various accounts through this app

Pioneered the space of Windows 8 initial launching apps for Microsoft Singapore; some were CNA, DBS Bank Singapore, and The Straits Times Singapore

Worked on various 2d and 3d games

Used and improved the Cocos2dx platform to flourish 2d games on cross-platform technologies

Written several frameworks myself and open-sourced them later to help the community; To mention some: EasyNDK-for-cocos2dx, Easy-CURL-for-PHP

Gelled along with various individual contributors to help the organization meet its financial goal

Presented learnings and findings at various university events and global technology events

Education

FAST - NUCES

2006 - 2010

Bachelor

Computer Science

Digital Logic Design	Assembly Language		Data Structures		Design Patterns
Web Programming	Compiler Construction		Concurrent and Distributed Systems		
High Performance Computing		Database De	atabase Design		

Awards

1 May 2015

IASA IT Architecture Core (ITAC) – CITAF Certification Iasa Global

Anchors to the beginning of Architect position and responsibilities

Won the GIKI SOFTCOM 08 (Programming Competition) **GIKI University Pakistan** A speed programming competition of national level Skills Web Development Expert HTML Javascript Software Architecture Advanced Scalability Design-patterns Distributed systems Maintainability Software Development **Proficient** Sustainability Portability Scalability Reasonability **Problem Solving** Advanced CompetitiveProgramming Abstract Draft documentation Proficient docsify Github MARP Joplin MermaidJS FormsIO Communication Competent face-2-face emails presentations conference buy-in talks negotiations layman conversions 1:1s Languages Urdu **English** Native speaker Fluent Interests Home improvements & engineering Plumbing Electric-appliances Civil engineering Software based home solutions raspberry-pi IoT Home-server plex cups saned Watching documentaries

1 April 2008

Idiocracy Lord-of-the-rings movies documentaries

References

"Amir is surely missed by his team/peers and I think any company would find great benefit with the addition of Amir to their leadership and technical team. Wish you all the best Amir and hope our paths cross again."

Heinrich Rust

"As a colleague Amir is friendly, personable, has an easy manner and great sense of humour. A clear communicator with a voice for radio, Amir is wise head on young shoulders."

Paul Fitzgerald